<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The main points of church-government and discipline; plainly and modestly handled by way of question and answer. Very useful to such as either want money to buy, or leasure to read larger tracts.</title>
            <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1182_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208163</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867142</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867142</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119433</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119433)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 167:E1182[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The main points of church-government and discipline; plainly and modestly handled by way of question and answer. Very useful to such as either want money to buy, or leasure to read larger tracts.</title>
                  <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Luke Favvne, and are to be sold at his shop at the Parrot ni [sic] pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Christopher Love.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A plain platform of Presbyterial government.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 17 1648"; the 9 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119433:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Main Points OF <hi>Church-Government</hi> AND DISCIPLINE; Plainly and modeſtly handled by way of Queſtion and Anſwer. Very uſeful to ſuch as either want Money to buy, or Leaſure to read larger Tracts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for LUKE FAVVNE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Parrot</hi> ni <hi>pauls</hi> Church-yard 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119433:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119433:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the worth of the Author, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of the matter of this book might ſufficiently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it ſelf unto thy peruſal, yet I ſhall add this to its Commendation, that 'tis plain, but profitable, ſhort,
<pb facs="tcp:119433:3"/>
but ſound: ſo that I may ſay of it as Tully did of Brutus his Laconical Epiſtle, <hi>Quam multa, quam paucis!</hi> how much in a little? Here is a great deal of matter in a few words; he ſtudyed brevity, yet ſolidity, in this ſmall piece; by the reading whereof not only the weak may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, but the ſtrong alſo eſtabliſht in the truth, which is the hearty deſire of him who ſubſcribes himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, CHRISTOPHER LOVE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119433:3"/>
            <head>A plain <hi>PLATFORM</hi> OF Presbyterial Government, <hi>Catechistically and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically propounded.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>QUEST. I. <hi>WHat Government of the Church is moſt agreeable to the Word of GOD?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Government of the Church by Presbyters or Elders for <hi>they have the rule,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 13. 7, 17. 1 Tim. 5. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the keys</hi> (which in the very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them do carry power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119433:4"/>
properly ſo called <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa, 22, 22 Rev. 1. 18, &amp; 3, 7.</note>) <hi>are committed to them</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 16. 19</note>, and power to <hi>remit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſins</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">John 20, 28</note>, <hi>they feed and govern the flock</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 2 Act. 20, 17 28</note>, and <hi>are over the people in the Lord</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5 12</note>; they are Guides, Leaders, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Governors, Paſtors; which Titles in Scripture are uſed to expreſſe the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Civill Magiſtrates <note n="g" place="margin">Joſh 13. 21. Numb. 31. 14. Mat. 27. 2. Jud. 8, 14. Acts 23, 14.</note>: Hence the Angels, the Elders of the Churches, are commended for good Diſcipline and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended for bad. <note n="h" place="margin">Rev. 2. 2, 6, 14, 20, &amp; Rev. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>What kind of Government have Presbyters or Elders over the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not Kingly, Lordly, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial power, which onely belongs to Chriſt <note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 5, 3. 1 Cor. 8. 6. &amp; 12. 5 Pſal. 2, 6, Col. 1. 18. Eph. 2, 22.</note>, but Stewardly and Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, <note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1. 2 Cor. 5 20. Mat. 9. 38.</note>.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>From whom receive they their Stewardly and Miniſteriall Power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> From Jeſus Chriſt <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 16. 19. &amp; 28, 18, 19, 20. Ioh. 20. 21, 23. 2 Cor. 8. 10:</note>, they are his Stewards <note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor, 4, i.</note>, his Miniſters and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors <note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 1. 2 Cor. 5. 19, 20.</note>, having their Office from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119433:4"/>
him <note n="o" place="margin">Eph 4. 8. 11. 1 Cor. 12. 28. Act. 20. 28, 29.</note>, and they are to act in his name <note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 18. 19 1 Cor. 5. 4, 5.</note>, and muſt give account to him <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 13, 17, 18. Luc. 12. 41, 42.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>But do they not receive their Governing Power and Authority from the Church or Body of the People?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, though they be for the good and benefit of the General Viſible Church, and of particular Churches <note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 4. 7 10, 11, 12 2 Cor. 12. 14</note>, and ought to make themſelves ſervants thereunto, as Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles (which did not receive their authority from thence) did <note n="s" place="margin">Math 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26, 27, 28 2 Cor. 4. 5 Col. 1. 7.</note>; and though they be elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the people, yet they do not receive their Authoritie from them. For, 1. the power of Church-Government is not conveighed to the body of the people, by any authentick grant or Commiſſion from Jeſus Chriſt, as it is to the Officers. 2. The people are not called Governors, Guides, Leaders, as the Officers are; but on the contrary, are called the flock <note n="t" place="margin">Acts 20. 28. 1 Pet. 5. 2</note>, the Saints <note n="u" place="margin">Hebr. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 24. Phi 1. 1</note>, as diſtinct from their Biſhops, Paſtors, Rulers, to whom they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſubject and obedient <note n="w" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5. 12 1 Tim. 5 17. Heb<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13. 7, 17.</note>. 3. The people have not received from Chriſt due gifts and qualifications for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119433:5"/>
exerciſe of Government and juriſdiction <note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 4, 5, 17 28, 29</note> as Officers have <note n="y" place="margin">Ephel 4. 11, 12 1 Tim 4. 14</note>. 4. It cannot be ſhewed that God in the Old or New Teſtament did erect any Church without Officers, ſeeing <hi>Adam</hi> was a Prieſt to his wife <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 3 Ainſworth.</note> and family (as <hi>Noah</hi> alſo was,) and the firſt born were Prieſts <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 19 22</note> at the founding of the Jewiſh Church, and Chriſt his Apoſtles were Officers in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion at the founding of the Chriſtian Churches. 5. It is more abſurd and irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, that all the males ſhould govern in a Church, then in a City or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; that the Elders ſhould be ſubject to the people, then that Magiſtrates ſhould be ſubject to their ſubjects; ſeeing the power of Church-government is derived not from the Law of Nature, which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Originall of Civill Government in the people, but the Canon of Scripture, which ſaith no ſuch thing concerning Church-Government. Nor, 6. doth it warrant, that the people ſhould exerciſe power and authority, in Preaching, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining, Adminiſtration of Sacraments or cenſures, therefore they have it not; for ſuch power is vain and impertinent, as may not be drawn into act by them that have it; and therefore Paſtors, Preaching, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119433:5"/>
Ordaining, &amp;c. do not put forth the peoples power, but the power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Jeſus Chriſt. <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 13 10. Math. 28. 19, 20</note>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>You ſpake of a General Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church; doth the Scripture hold out ſuch a Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, for, 1. The Apoſtles, which were General Officers (to which a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Church is the adequate correlative) and had the <hi>care of all the Churches</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 11 28</note>, are ſaid to <hi>ſet,</hi> put or placed, <hi>in the Church</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 28</note>, as ſpeaking but of one; <hi>Paul</hi> was a Miniſter of this Church <note n="f" place="margin">Col. 1. 25</note>. 2. That <hi>one body,</hi> that <hi>one fold,</hi> into which all, both Jews and Gentiles, are Baptized and brought <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 12, 13. Eph 2. 16. &amp; 36 Joh. 10 16</note>, maſt needs be the univerſall viſible Church. 3. That houſe or Temple, in which Antichriſt did ſit <note n="h" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2. 4</note>, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man travelling <note n="i" place="margin">Rev. 12. 1 2. &amp;c.</note>, the Bride and Spouſe of Chriſt <note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 21. 2</note>, a child, and in non-age un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and at full age under the Goſpell <note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 4. 1, 2</note>, that aſſembly of 24 Elders and 4 Beaſts <note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 4.</note>, that one Sion having many Aſſemblies in it <note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 4. 5</note>, that one City, one new Jeruſalem <note n="o" place="margin">Rev. 20. 9. &amp; 21. 2</note>, that one Feaſt <note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 22. 2</note>, field <note n="q" place="margin">Mit. 13. 24.</note>, floor <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 3. 12.</note>, draw-net <note n="s" place="margin">Math. 13. 47</note>, and the like, are to be underſtood of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Viſible Church, which is further
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119433:6"/>
in Scripture deſcribed to be Organi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 14 &amp;c. Rom. 12. 4 to 9. Epheſ. 4 4. with 11, 12.</note>.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>But we read of</hi> Churches <note n="v" place="margin">Gal 1. 2. 1 Cor. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 34. Acts 9. 31.</note> 
               <hi>in the plurall number, of many Churches in the New Teſtament, and therefore there is not onely one Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Theſe are the particular Churches I ſpake of, of the ſame name and nature with the whole, as the Sea is but one <note n="w" place="margin">Pſa. 95. 5</note>, yet the ſeverall parts of it, waſhing ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhoars, are called Seas <note n="x" place="margin">Pſa. 24 2</note>, the dry Land but one <note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 1. 10</note>, yet being poſſeſt by ſeverall Nations, under ſeveral climates, divided by hills, rivers, and other bounda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, is called Lands <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 10 31</note>, as <hi>Labans</hi> flocks, having all one owner, and probably all one mark, are called one flock <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 30. 31, 32, 36, 38. &amp; 33. 13</note>, as the free men of <hi>Rome,</hi> where ever born or bred, make but one Corporation <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 22. 3 with 28</note>; hence the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> though a compleat particular Church, is not called the whole <hi>City</hi> or <hi>houſhold</hi> of God, but <hi>fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens with the Saints,</hi> viz. of other Churches, and <hi>of the</hi> houſhold. As the Jewiſh Church was but <hi>one,</hi> yet in regard of their Sabbath-convocations in their Synagogues <note n="d" place="margin">Lev. 23. 1, 2, 3</note>, for hearing the Word
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119433:6"/>
read <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 15. 21</note>, and preached <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 13. 14, 15, 16</note>, for prayer <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 16. 13</note>, for Rule and Government <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 13. 15. Joh 12 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. 34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. 1, 2</note>, was called <hi>Congregations</hi> &amp; <hi>Churches</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſa. 26. 12. &amp; 68 26. &amp; 74 4, 8</note>. As the Antichriſtian Churches of <hi>Italy, Spain, Germany,</hi> are but one <hi>Where</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17 5. &amp; 18. 2 3. &amp; 19. 2</note>, under one head the Pope, ſo the Chriſtian Churches of <hi>England, Scotland, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>have their Fathers name written in their foreheads</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rev. 14. 1</note>, are but one <hi>woman</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 12. 1</note>; the one is the <hi>army</hi> under the <hi>Dragon,</hi> the other under <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rev. 12 7</note>: and as a whole <hi>Army</hi> is oft times in the Originall Language of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called a <hi>Church</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 47 Ezek. 16, 40. Jer. 50 9</note>, and the ſeverall Regiments and Companies are called <hi>Churches</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eze 26, 7</note>, ſo particular Churches and Antichriſtian conventions, are as the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Brigades, Regiments, or Companie of thoſe two Armies: Hence alſo the Church of God is called <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Cant. 6, 10, 13</note>, <hi>Vineyard</hi> and <hi>Vineyards</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Cant. 7, 12 <hi>&amp;</hi> 8, 11, 12</note>, <hi>Garden</hi> and <hi>Gardens</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 6, 2</note>, as well as Church and Churches.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>What ſorts of Elders hath God appointed in his Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Two ſorts; extraordinary, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet, 5, 1 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Joh. <hi>v.</hi> 1</note>; and ordinary, as <hi>Paſtors</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119433:7"/>
               <hi>Teachers</hi> 
               <note n="v" place="margin">Acts 20 17, 28. Tit. 1, 5</note>. The Apoſtles were to Teach and Rule, not onely Churches, but Paſtors and Miniſters alſo, being men of an higher order <note n="w" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 28. Eph. 4 11</note>, immediatly called of God <note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 1, 1</note>, infallible in their doctrine <note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 1, 7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5, 2</note>, endowed with extraordinary gifts <note n="z" place="margin">Acts 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8, 17 18</note>, ſaw Chriſt in the fleſh <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 1, 21 1 Cor. 9, 1</note>, were injoyned ordinarily to travel abroad to plant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 28 19</note>, might act authoritatively in any Church without a call or conſent of men, and might ſhake the duſt off their feet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch Miniſters, or others, as did not receive them <note n="c" place="margin">Math. 10 14</note>, their commiſſion was irrepealable, the limits they agreed on were large <note n="d" place="margin">Gal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2, 9</note>. But a Miniſter is not of an higher order, nor hath power over his fellow Miniſters, nor hath an immediate irrepealable Call, not infallible, nor in theſe times extraordinarily gifted, hath not ſeen Jeſus Chriſt in the fleſh, cannot exerciſe paſtoral authority in an ordinary or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal way without a call and conſent of perſons intereſted. And laſtly, Paſtors and Teachers are by ſucceſſion to continue in the Church to the end of the world <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 4, 11, 12 Rev. 12, 6 &amp; 11, 2, 3</note>, whereas Apoſtleſhip continued in one age only; for though <hi>Matthias</hi> was ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in the room of <hi>Judas</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act. 1, 25</note>, yet none was ſubſtituted in the room of <hi>James</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 12, 2</note>,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119433:7"/>
or of any other Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>In what Church hath God ſet theſe Elders?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the Univerſal Church pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 28. Eph. 4 11. Ro 12</note>, and in particular Churches ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarily <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 13, 1</note>: Diviſion of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to particular Congregations, and fixing particular Elders to them, is no further of divine inſtitution then order and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did firſt occaſion, and do ſtill require it ſhould be ſo, as the whole Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> ſed all the Jews in common, (for ought we know) while they were together: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (it may be) the four Families of <hi>Levites,</hi> as <hi>Aaron, Cohath, Gerſhon, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari,</hi> did take more ſpecial charge of thoſe Tribes that quartered on the ſame ſide of the Tabernacle that they did <note n="k" place="margin">Num. 2, 3, 10, 18, 25. with Numb 3, 38, 10, 18, 25 Sec <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> in Num. 2</note>, and then there was ſome diviſion made, and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that a further diviſion was made, when the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came to be fixed in their ſeveral diviſions, and the <hi>Levites</hi> alſo were ſcattered and fixed amongſt them for the better inſtruction of the people, and had their maintenance by Lands and Tythes where they lived. So the Apoſtles notwithſtanding their general commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note n="l" place="margin">Math. 28 19, 20 Mar. 16</note>, did feet the Church in common, while there was but one particular
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119433:8"/>
Church, and afterwards when Churches were multiplyed, did for edification and orders ſake agree upon a diviſion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 2, 9</note>, (though they were not very preciſe in obſerving it, <hi>Peter</hi> preaching ſometimes to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Jews,)</hi> and had their ſeveral places or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily to officiate in <note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 10 13, 14, 15, 16</note>, yea ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably think, that they did diſperſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into twelve parts of the world, and the Greek text <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 1. 25</note> may (if you put the comma after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) fully bear this ſenſe, that <hi>Mathias might be ſent that circuit which Judas, had he not fallen, ſhould have gone;</hi> and in likelyhood it was from this agreement, that <hi>James</hi> (notwithſtanding his Apoſtolik commiſſion was as general as the comiſſion of the other Apoſtles) did not travel abroad as the other did, but ſtayd at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> as alſo ſome other Apoſtles af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their travels betook themſelves to reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ſome one place, as if they had been the fixed Paſtors of thoſe places reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thoſe Apoſtles that travelled abroad did carry Miniſters along with them, as <hi>John, Mark,</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 13, 5 &amp; 15, 37</note> their fellow laborer, <note n="q" place="margin">Philem. 24</note> and did ſend other Miniſters, as <hi>Tychicus,</hi> ſometimes to one Church, as <hi>Epheſus</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Act. 20, 4 Eph. 6, 21, 22</note>, and ſometimes to another, as <hi>Colloſs,</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Col. 4, 7</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119433:8"/>
and did keep other Miniſters from their particular charges, as <hi>Epaphras</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Col. 1, 7 with 4. 12</note> and all this was for the ſervice of the univerſal Church, ſo much was it preferred before the ſervice of their particular Churches. In the primitive times before diviſion of titles, the Elders were not affixed to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular aſſemblies, but the officers did in common teach and govern ſundry congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; and ſo it may be at this day, when it ſhall be found moſt for edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo it is in ſome Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: As the Juſtices of Peace have their commiſſion for the whole County, yet by agreement or cuſtom for order-ſake, they have their ſeveral Hundreds or diviſions, in which they keep their privy and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Seſſions, and do ordinarily execute their office, and in that reſpect may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Juſtices of ſuch a Diviſion or Circuit; And as the Militia Soldiers, which watch and guard the City of <hi>London,</hi> are prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the Soldiers of the whole City; and ſecundarily the Soldiers of ſuch and ſuch a Ward or limits; ſo Miniſters, which are called watchmen and ſoldiers <note n="v" place="margin">Iſa. 62. 6 1 Tim. 2, 3</note>, are Miniſters both of the whole City of God, the univerſal viſible Church, and alſo of thoſe particular Churches or Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119433:9"/>
which they eſpecially take charge of and receive maintenance from, and as Souldiers, though they be the Souldiers of the whole City, yet each have and ought in reaſon to have one particular place aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be guarded by him, and the unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable abſence of him from his guard is cenſurable; ſo a Miniſter ſhould have his flock, and be reſident with it.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>How are men made ordinary Elders?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are made Elders by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which is (as the Scripture defines it) <hi>an appointment of men over the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">Act. 6, 3</note> the ſeven Deacons had not been Officers though choſen by the multitude, if they had not been by Ordination ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed over the buſineſs, the multitude chooſing them is not ſaid to appoint them over the buſineſs, but to <hi>ſet them before the Apoſtles.</hi> 2. Hence the charge is more expreſs, that ordination rather then election ſhould not ſuddenly and haſtily be made <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 5 22</note>, whereas if election had only or chiefly made the Officer; then prudence had required, that the charge ſhould have been more expreſs againſt haſty election then haſty ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 3. Laying on of hands in ordination, not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119433:9"/>
lifting up of hands in election (which they ſo much urge) is reckoned amongſt the principles <note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 6, 3</note>. 4. The deſcription of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fit for office is much more large in the Epiſtles to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> which were to ordain, then in any or all the Epiſtles written to the Churches, to whom electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is conceived to belong <note n="z" place="margin">1 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 3 2, &amp;c. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12, &amp;c. Tit. 1, 5, 6, 7, 8, &amp;c.</note>; now the Apoſtle, which did all things fitly, would acquaint thoſe moſt with the qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of officers, which had the greateſt hand and power in making officers. 5. Faſting &amp; prayer is to beg direction &amp; aſſiſtance from God, with reference to ordination, rather then election <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 13 1, 2</note>; the Apoſtles prayed not before the election of the ſeven Deacons, (as they would, if that had been of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtmoment,) but the Scripture witneſſeth, that when the election was paſt they pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before ordination <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 6. 5. 6</note>. 6. The Scripture ſpeaks much and plainly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ordination, <note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. 4 14. Tit. 1. 5 Act. 14. 23 Act. 13. 1, 2 1 Tim. 5, 22 2 Tim. 2, 2</note>, &amp; but little, (ſome ſay, nothing at all) and that obſcurely for popular election of Elders. 7. The peoples election is but prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory to the making of Elders, or a nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or deſignation of ſome perſons to that office, if being tryed by the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry they be approved as fit; God having <note place="margin">d 1 Tim. 5 22</note> given ſpecial power and charge to the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119433:10"/>
Presbytery not to ordain raſhly <hi>(d)</hi> or ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 22</note> though the people ſhould elect raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to reject that raſh election as null and void. 8. To aſſert, that Miniſters are made by ordination, doth make the line of miniſterial power more ſtraight and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar then otherwiſe; the power of making Miniſters was firſt in Chriſt, and he made Apoſtles; they, as his ſtewards in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and by his direction and command, do appoint other officers, Chriſt is the chief Paſtor <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 2 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, the Apoſtles next <note n="f" place="margin">Joh. 21, 15, 16, 17</note>, then Elders <note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 5, 2 Act. 20, 17 28</note>, Chriſt the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 25</note> Apoſtles, Biſhops <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 1, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note n="k" place="margin">Acts 20 17, 18. Tit. 1, 7</note>, Chriſt was ſent and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 20, 21</note>, and Presbyters <note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 4. 8, 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, Chriſt ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twelve <note n="n" place="margin">Mark 3, 14. Ioh. 15, 14</note>, and the twelve ordained El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note n="o" place="margin">Acts 14, 23</note>, and to Elders hath God given the power of ordination of other Elders ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. 10. To whom, ſay you, hath God committed the power of ordination of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To Elders <note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 4 14. Tit. 1, 5. <hi>ut ſupra</hi>
               </note>: not to any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>officied man; For 1. there is no precept nor warrant for it in all the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Chriſt or his Apoſtles did leave
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119433:10"/>
to the body of beleevers, Elders the power of ordaining, though it had bin much eaſier to have writ to the Churches, that they ſhould ordain their own Elders, then to ave traveled themſelves <note n="q" place="margin">Acts 14 23</note>, or to have ſent <hi>Timothy</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> for that purpoſe <note n="r" place="margin">1 Tim. 5 22. Tit. 1 5</note>. 2. Not one inſtance can be given of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>officed man, ordaining an officer of the New Teſtament. 3. They that do ordain do put ſome of their work upon the perſon ordeined, but preaching, baptizing, &amp;c. is not the work of any unofficed man. 4. He that ordains bleſſeth him that is ordained, and the leſs is bleſſed of the greater <note n="s" place="margin">Heb. 7, 7</note>. 5. Ordination is confeſſed to be an act of authority, and an unofficed man have not authority. 6. The Church cannot lawfully depute a man to ordain whom God hath not deputed, nor can the man or men ſo deputed lawfully ordain, except the Church have a Charter from God to that effect. 7. There is not one of a thouſand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people that are able in all points to try and judg of the ſufficiency of preaching Presbyters, as they that ordain are bound by Gods Law to do <note n="t" place="margin">Tit. 1, 5, 6, 7</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. 11. But is not ordination by one or more grave men deputed by the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation more lawful, and valid then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119433:11"/>
by the Prelates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, the Biſhops were Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſo more enabled by the Word to ordain then any non-Presbyters: Prelacy, though an humane Inſtitution, did no more annihilate their being Presbyters, then Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaiſm did the Jewiſh Prieſt-hood, and they did ordain as Presbyters; for Biſhops and Presbyters are but made one order by the very Papiſts, which alſo judg, that if a Deacon ſhould be made a Biſhop <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaltum</hi> he hath no power to ordein Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters: The Elders ordeined by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in every City, did in their meetings chuſe one of their fellow Elders (if no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle nor Apoſtolick man did reſide with them, if they did, they by their places were ſuperior to any Presbyter and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derators in any convention of Elders, and ſo ſhould be at this day, if any Apoſtle were now alive and reſident) to be Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of their company and Moderator of their actions; now Preſidency is natural and neceſſary for the regulating of matters: <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith, it is ſcriptural, and that this Preſident was the ſame which S. <hi>John</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Angel, the continuance of preſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in one man was not then found to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlawful or inconvenient. To this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119433:11"/>
the Fathers afterward appropriated the name of Biſhop, and ſuch as theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grave men, and of great repute, and Paſtors of the chief Cities, and having the ſpirit of Government, (which every god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter hath not,) partly through their own uſurpation, partly through the ſloth and puſillanimity of the Presbyters, partly by Law and Canon, were inveſted with too much power; yet did not they, no nor our Engliſh Biſhops ordain Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, without the aſſiſtance of other Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and therefore their ordination comes neerer to the Scripture-way of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by the <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> then any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination by one or many non-Presbyters can do, (one two or three deputed Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers being nothing like a Presbytery, or a company of Presbyters,) and is by this preſent Parliament and Synod, as formerly, alſo by the reformed Churches, and godly non-conformiſts, (notwithſtanding their oppoſition to prelacy,) judged valid, and not to be changed for any popular ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; when the Church was in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, when Antichriſt moſt raigned and raged, God did preſerve ſome fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal doctrines, and the eſſence of Baptiſm, and the eſſence of a true Miniſtry diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119433:12"/>
it, and they, that is, her Paſtors <hi>did feed her there</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Rev. 12. 6. 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>Who have power to preach the Word in the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Paſtors and Teachers, that have alſo authority to baptize <note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 28 20.</note>. God having joyned them together, no man ought to put them aſunder <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 19. 16.</note>. 2. Preaching is a principal part of the Miniſterial Office <note n="y" place="margin">1 Per. 5. 2 1 Tim. 3. 2 2 Tim. 4 2</note>, requiring more ſufficiency then any other part <note n="z" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16</note>, (hence the ability of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectants is beſt tryed by preaching,) and of as much dignity and truſt as the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Sacraments <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 4. 1. 1 Cor. 1. 17</note>, which yet (is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed) may not be adminiſtred by private men. 3. God hath, by a ſpecial office, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed Miniſters from other men, and ſeparated them to be Paſtors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <note n="a" place="margin">Eph 4. 11</note>, and therefore this order is not to be violated, nor ſhould men enter in at the window, but by the door <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 10. 1 2</note>. 4. God hath ſeverely puniſht uſurpers of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial function <note n="c" place="margin">Num. 16 9. 10 1 Sam. 13. 9, 12, 13, 14</note>, yea when there ſeemed to be great neceſſity of it <note n="d" place="margin">1 San. 13 8 2 Sam. 6 6 7, 8, 9.</note>. 5. None ought to preach except they be ſent, and called thereunto <note n="e" place="margin">Rem. 10. 15. Ier. 23. 21. Heb. 5. 4, 5.</note>, but gifted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth not include in it ſufficient miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or vocation: For as women may be gifted, which yet are forbidden to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119433:12"/>
preach <note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor: 14 34. 1 Tim. 1. 11. 12.</note>; ſo no man may exerciſe Regal or Magiſtratical power, or do the office of a Conſtable, Lawyer, Attorney, a Reader in one of the Inns of Court, a Juſtice of Peace, a Judg, a Speaker in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, a Captain, Major, Colonel, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, only upon this ground, becauſe he is conceived to be gifted for it. 6. It is ſaid, God hath made his people Kings and Prieſts <note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 1. 6 1 Pet. 2. 5.</note>, but not that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hath made them Prophets; for though God did ſometimes give an immediate and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary commiſſion to do ſome Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratical acts <note n="h" place="margin">Num. 25 7, 8. Acts 5. 5.</note>, and the time was, when Gods Holy Spirit being extraordinarily poured out on all fleſh, their ſons and daughters did propheſie, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily anointed did ſo <note n="i" place="margin">Joel 2 28 with Acts 2 17.</note>, as they did alſo ſee viſions, and dream dreams; and then it was alſo mens duty to deſire any ſpiritual gifts, as ſpeaking with tongues, but eſpecially propheſie <note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 1, 2.</note>; but now it is unlawful to deſire the one gift, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; God not inabling gifted men now to underſtand the original languages as then he did. 7. Teaching in the Church doth imply authority over them that are taught <note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim 1. 11, 12.</note>; but private men, though gift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have not authority, therefore they are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119433:13"/>
not to <hi>teach or uſurp authority.</hi> 8. God hath not given them any power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive maintenance, which is due to thoſe that labor in the Word and Doctrine <note n="m" place="margin">1 Tim. 5 17, 18 1 Cor. 9. 3, 4, 5, 6, 9, 11</note>.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 13. <hi>What maintenance mean you? If you mean</hi> Tythes, or <hi>any other ſetled maintenance, neither private men nor Miniſters ought to receive ſuch maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Tythes had many enemies, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry exceptions made againſt the payment of them, nor was it counted any robbery to detain them <note n="n" place="margin">Mal. 3. 8 2 Chro. 31 4, 5, &amp;c.</note>, when both God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the Magiſtrates, did expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the due payment of them, and when there were few or no Sectaries, (at leaſt not in arms and authority,) which endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored the ruin of the Miniſtry, eſpecially when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but every man did that which was right in his own eyes; then the <hi>Levites</hi> were glad to wander abroad for maintenance <note n="o" place="margin">Iude 17, 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 8, 9. 10, 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19. 1</note>. Yet 2. the <hi>Levites,</hi> though a ſmall Tribe <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth</hi> in Num. 3. 39</note>, (if a Tribe, there being twelve beſides,) ſcarce the 60. part of the houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> had in <hi>Judea</hi> a ſmall Country, 48. Cities with their Suburbs, 2000. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites from the wall on every ſide <note n="q" place="margin">Ioſh. 21. 41. Num 35. 2. Lev. 25. 32, 33, 34</note>,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119433:13"/>
and their firſt fruits <note n="r" place="margin">Num 18. 15, 16, 17, 18. Deut. 18, 4.</note>, and a great part of the manifold ſacrifices <note n="s" place="margin">Lev. 2 3. &amp; 7. 5, 7, 8 33. 34</note>, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will offerings of all the males of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which were to appear thrice yearly before the Lord with ſome offering <note n="t" place="margin">Exod. 34 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 23. 15, 16, 17.</note>, and whatſoever houſe, field, perſon, beaſt, &amp;c. was by a ſingular vow given to the Lord, which was to be valued by the Prieſt himſelf <note n="v" place="margin">Lev. 27. 2, 3, 4. 5, 8, 9, 10, &amp;c.</note>, and all theſe duties were brought in to the Prieſt without charge or trouble; they had not only the full tenth of all kind of encreaſe, but alſo ſuch an impoſition layd upon all kind of grain, as came to more then a ſixth part of the crop it ſelf <note n="w" place="margin">Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> Aaron. 1. 6. c. 2, 3.</note>, and thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Lands deſcended from them to their poſterity from generation to gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as alſo did their Tythes and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. 3. Suppoſe Jeſus Chriſt, being a Member of the Jewiſh Church, did not demand the Tythes then due by Gods Law to the Levitical Prieſts <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 23. 23 Heb 7. 5</note>. Suppoſe alſo the Apoſtles being by their office to travel abroad, did not receive Tythes, (no more then the <hi>Levites</hi> did receive them in their travel,) but were ſometimes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to take ſo much as a ſcrip <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 10. 10.</note>, (though at other times allowed it <note n="z" place="margin">Luc. 22. 35, 36.</note>,) and enjoyned to live at the charges of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119433:14"/>
faithful <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 10. 10, 11</note>; and though <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> did ſometimes work with their hands that they might not be chargeable <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 6.</note>, yet <hi>Paul</hi> doth expreſly affirm, that Tythes were not Aaronical, or proper to the Levitical Prieſts, but on the contrary proves the greatneſs of <hi>Melchizede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s Prieſthood, by his bleſſing <hi>Abraham,</hi> and tything him <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 7. 2, 4, 5, 7.</note>; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">verſe 6.</note> implyes, requiring Tythes, as well as receiving them, and thereupon he aſſerts our Saviour to be a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchizedec</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">v. 15, 16, 17</note>; and therefore Chriſt muſt needs have power to tythe the people as well as to bleſs them, or elſe he comes not up to the type or figure: he therefore that ſaith Tythes are Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, muſt ſhew wherein the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doth conſiſt, and upon what Scripture he grounds his opinion, and anſwer <hi>Paul</hi>'s argument, or elſe he is to be eſteemed a deluder of the people, ſuppoſing that gain is godlineſs <note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 6 5</note>. 4. The Miniſtry of the New Teſtament, being far more honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor 3. 6, 7, &amp;c.</note>, laborious and ſtudious, then the Levitical Prieſthood, and the Miniſters of the Goſpel being to live of the Goſpel <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 13, 14</note>, they have an evil eye that grudg the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſo much means
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119433:14"/>
proportionably, as the Prieſts had under the Law, that judg 100. l. <hi>per annum;</hi> or more, little enough for a Factor, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough or too much for a Miniſter, <hi>A principio non fuit ſic;</hi> for Beleevers had all things common <note n="h" place="margin">Acts 432</note>, and ſo far they were from grudging the tenth part of their encreaſe, that they ſold their Lands, and laid the prizes of them at the Apoſtles feet <note n="i" place="margin">v. 34, 35.</note>; and afterwards, by one means or other, Miniſters had, in perſecuting times, (much more ought they to have in peaceable and proſperous times,) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly competent but honorable maintenance <note n="k" place="margin">1 Tim 5 17, 18</note>, for themſelves, their wives and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 9, 4, 5, 6 1 Tim. 3, 4 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5, 8</note>, and to keep hoſpitality <note n="m" place="margin">Tit. 1. 8</note>, and all this without entangling themſelves in the affairs of this life <note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 4</note>.</p>
            <p>As for the Tythes, with relation to this Kingdom, (omitting how far the Law of nature, one of the fundamentals of our Laws, did teach them the Gentiles,) it is unqueſtionable that they, in ſome Pariſhes at leaſt, are the Miniſters right, by as good Law as the 9. parts are the peoples; and it is as illegal for the people to with-hold their tenth's, as if the Miniſter ſhould, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his tenth's, take away one or more of their 9. parts; and it is perillous to a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119433:15"/>
State, that private men ſhould prefer their judgment of <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> of right and wrong, before the publick judgment of the Law and Courts of the Kingdom, and may be as deſtructive to Nobility, Gentry, and others in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to have the hedg of the Law broken down, as it is to the Miniſtry; ſundry perſons (ſome whereof are in power and place) being as inclinable to defraud them alſo of the Tythes, and to introduce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality and community in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as in the Church.</p>
            <p>2. This Law of Tythes was not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on the people, as ſome falſly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, but a voluntary donation, not of the <hi>people</hi> (though, if they that were then owners of the land, and had power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate them in whole, or in part, and did ſo, that is a ſufficient bar againſt thoſe in whoſe hands they now are, which have no title but what they hold from and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and can juſtly claim no more then was tranſmitted by them,) but of the <hi>King,</hi> who then having all the Lands in <hi>England</hi> in demeſne, did give the tenth part of his own Lands, or, as ſome call it, <hi>the tenth part of his Kingdom,</hi> to the Church, and were conſented unto, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119433:15"/>
have been ſince payd, as a rent-charge on the Land, before the Subject, either Lord or Tenant, had any thing at all to do in the ſaid Lands; and therefore whether or no the Scripture doth preſcribe the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular way of Miniſters maintenance, in Corn, a ſeventh, eighth, ninth, tenth, or eleventh part, more or leſs, or in moneys, yearly, quarterly, monethly, weekly, payd by Tax or Contribution, or in Lands, or in ſome, or all of theſe, it is not much material; For though (ſuppoſe) before <hi>they gave it, it was in their own power,</hi> (which was the caſe of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phirah</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 5. 4</note>,) yet the Tythes being ſo given, it is grievous ſin to alienate them from their general end: For firſt, it is ſacriledg to <hi>devour that which is holy,</hi> or devoted to the ſervice of God and the Church <note n="p" place="margin">Prov 20 25 Levit. 27. 28, 30</note> though this ſacriledg be committed upon pretence of Reformation and hatred of Idols <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 2, 22</note>. Secondly, it is a diſanulling of the teſtament of men <note n="r" place="margin">Gal. 3. 15</note>, when it is confirmed not only by the Doners or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtators, but by ſeveral Acts of Parliament, <hi>Magna Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> and late Ordinances. Thirdly, it wilfully incurs thoſe direful Execrations which were uſually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt all ſuch Church-robbers;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119433:16"/>
and in ſome places, where Tythes are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly withheld from the Miniſters, God himſelf doth, as it were, tythe their corn, and take away at leaſt the tenth part of it, that they ſee they are no gainers by this unjuſt courſe: And theſe things are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the ſatisfaction, not of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous (whereof there is little hope,) but of the conſcientious, and not for any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Author, whoſe means (for his own particular) would be much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if no Tythes at all were payd, then now they are.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, As for ſetled maintenance: 1. The Scripture doth allude to a certain and ſetled maintenance that ſhould be given to the Miniſtry <note n="s" place="margin">Ezek. 45 1, 5</note>, in comparing it with ſervants hire and wages <note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim 5 18</note>, and a ſoldiers pay <note n="v" place="margin">1 Cor. 9 7</note>, both which are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. 2. God doubtleſs hath as much care of the maintenance of the Miniſters of the New Teſtament, as of the Old; ſhall we then think that he did allow the one certain maintenance, which none could deprive them of, and make the other uncapable of ſuch maintenance? 3. When a Miniſter hath ſet-maintenance he knows better how to proportion his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, his alms, his expences for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119433:16"/>
his proviſion for his children, and how to keep hoſpitality. 4. Tythes are not, in one ſence, ſetled or ſtinted main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, for they are more or leſs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Husbandman ſoweth, and God proſpereth; as Corn is little or much, good or bad, well or ill gotten, dear or cheap: they that do receive Tythes do riſe or fall with them that pay them. 5. Magiſtrates ſhould be nurſing Fathers and Mothers to the Church <note n="w" place="margin">Iſai. 49 23</note>: they ſhould bring their glory and honor into it <note n="x" place="margin">Rev. 21 24, 26</note>: And may they not aſſign certain maintenance to the Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which they may do to their meaneſt ſervants, yea to to the meaneſt men in the Kingdom, if ſo they pleaſe? But of this enough.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 14. <hi>Who may lawfully be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that profeſs Faith and Repentance <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 3, 6 7. Acts 2, 41, 47 Acts 8, 37<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, (I ſpeak of Jews, Heathens, and other ſtrangers to the Church, not of children born within the Church, which may be baptized before any ſuch perſonal profeſſion, and are to be accounted within the Church by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their parents being within the Church,) except there be ſome juſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119433:17"/>
ground of perſonal prejudice againſt them, as in the caſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> whom the Apoſtles might well ſuſpect to be ſtill a Jew, a Perſecutor, and a Spy, and that he but aſſay'd to joyn himſelf to them to atchieve his wicked ends, till they heard <hi>Barnabas</hi> his teſtomony concerning him <note n="z" place="margin">Act 9 26 27, 28</note>. But ſecondly, there is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or preſident of the calling of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (before they could be admitted into the Church) to give account of the work of grace in their heart, or of a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation judging whether that work was wrought or no, or of their meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for prayer and mutual conference, to be ſatisfied of the good eſtate one of another, or of their deferring admiſſion till they had ſuch ſatisfaction; nor did Jeſus Chriſt (as man) know <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the region round a-<hi>Jordan,</hi> with whom he was baptized <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 3, 6 7</note>, nor were <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> the Apoſtles, and thoſe thouſands and myriades which they baptized, ſatisfied in their conſciences of the regeneration each of other, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing each other to be a real Saint; nor did the Jewiſh Church (though called Saints) <note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 89. 5 7. Pſa. 149 1. Exo. 19 5, 6</note> conſiſt only of ſuch which were, at leaſt in the judgment of Charity, ſincere
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119433:17"/>
Converts; nor doth <hi>Pauls</hi> writing to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> called to be Saints, evince, that at the time of his writing to them (much leſs before or after) he did judg the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church to conſiſt wholy of true Saints, the contrary is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3 1, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5, 1, 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 11 21. 2 Cor. 12, 20, 21 1 Cor. 15 34</note>. The Churches charity is but a leaden rule, no certain one; ſome mens charity being more, ſome leſs <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 15. 37, 38, 39</note>, and the ſame mens charity being larger at ſometimes then at others, and to ſome men, as thoſe of their own opinions, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, benefactors, &amp;c. then to others; whence it followeth that ſome men may ſometimes lawfully admit ſuch, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea themſelves, at other times, may lawfully reject; the caſe, in it ſelf, being the very ſame.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 15. <hi>How come particular Churches to be one in themſelves, and to be diſtinguiſhed one from another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Their habitation is in this caſe conſiderable; it being agreeable to the Law of Nature and Scripture, that there ſhould be Pariſhes, or Churches ſhould be confined within convenient local limits: For 1. elſe the members of a particular Church migh live 10. 20. 50, an 100. miles each from other without
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119433:18"/>
blame. 2. The word conſtantly holds forth, that the <hi>Chriſtian inhabitants</hi> of a City, Town, or place, were <hi>the Church</hi> in that City, Town, or place. 3. Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are uſually denominated from places, as the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem, Rome, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> do expound one another <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 14 23. Titus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1, 5. Acts 16, 4, 5</note>. 4. They that did remove their habitations, did (it's ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable) fall into memberſhip with thoſe Churches whither they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 18, 2 24, 25, 26 Rom. 16, 2</note>. 5. If, Church members be not reſident amongſt themſelves, how can Paſtors be reſident amongſt them <note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet 5, 2</note>? 6. Cohabitation of Church-members hath divers paterns in Scripture uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled by precepts and other paterns; For no inſtance can be ſhewed: that any dwelt neerer to one true Church (though corrupt, as <hi>Corinth, Laodicea, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, &amp;c.)</hi> and was a member of a Church in another City or Town, as <hi>Cenchrea;</hi> or that any dwelt within the civil comunion of the members of a Church, (which is oft for worldly ends) and was not a member of that Church; or that Chriſtians, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling remote one from another, were of one particular Congregation. 7. That none but thoſe that cohabite ſhould be of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119433:18"/>
one Congregation, is required by Reaſon, as well as Scripture: 1. For their more commodious meeting together in publick with eaſe, frequency, leſs expence of time and money. 2. Their more eaſie conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with, watching over, comforting and relieving one another. 3. For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of confuſion, contention, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. 4. For the more convenient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection over their Families, that their Families, as well as themſelves, do ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Sabbath; and therefore if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate do command, that Churches ſhould have ſuch and ſuch convenient bounds, his command is to be obſerved, being according to Scripture and right Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe Chriſtians, thus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting, are to chuſe, or to ſubmit unto, and maintain the ſame individual Church-Officers, frequent the ſame numerical Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and other Ordinances, and ſo are eaſily enough diſtinguiſhed from thoſe Churches, the members whereof dwell elſewhere, and ſubmit to other Officers, and frequent other meeting places for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and other Ordinances: <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> aſſembling themſelves a whole year with the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119433:19"/>
are ſaid to be within that Church <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 11, 26, with 13, 1</note>: And this was the primitive way; When many Chriſtians were converted in a Town or City, the Apoſtles ordeined them Elders <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 14 23</note>; and the Elders and Chriſtian inhabitants, mutually perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the duties of their places, became a Church together, ſufficiently diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from others; and this is far from the Church-covenant urged by ſome, it being only an agreement implyed in actions, as when a man dwells in a Town, joyns in chuſing Conſtables and other Offices, pays Lays and Taxes, aſſiſts Officers, and bears Office, if required, doth tacitly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that he is one of that Town; and yet we cannot ſay that he hath entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to covenant, or that entring into cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant doth make him ſo.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 16. <hi>How large or how little may particular Churches be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Church muſt conſiſt of more then two or three (though when there was no more in the world but <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> they two made a Church if there was any) for two or three were to give the ſecond Admonition which if a man did not, here they were to tell the Church <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 18 15, 16, 17.</note> and therefore the Church muſt of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119433:19"/>
neceſſity conſiſt of more then two or three: yea, there ſhould be in a Church a competent number to be Officers and Members, at leaſt the Members ſhould be as a Flock, that is, many, though there were no Officer, but one Paſtor: The Churches in the Goſpel were numer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, conſiſting of thouſands, and that they might do ſo, the Apoſtles planted Churches only in <hi>Cities,</hi> and in great Towns; <hi>Cenchrea,</hi> the leaſt, was a much frequented populous and famous Haven-Town <note n="g" place="margin">Gualter <hi>in</hi> Rom. 16</note>, ſo alſo were the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Galatia, Macedonia, Judea,</hi> placed in the Cities of thoſe Countries, as <hi>Antioch; Laodicea, Philippi, Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, Jeruſalem, Lidda, &amp;c.</hi> and how numerous ſoever any Church did grow, we read not that it was divided into two or more Churches, or that there were more Churches then one in any one City or Town. As it is acknowledged on all hands, that a particular Church may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of as many as may meet every Lords day in oue place for edification; ſo it may be proved, that the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did conſiſt of more, then did or could meet with edification in one place. 1. By the multitude of Beleevers, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119433:20"/>
and all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the region round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Jordan,</hi> were baptized by <hi>John</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 3. 6 7</note>; and the Diſciples of Chriſt baptized more Diſciples then <hi>John</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 4. 1</note>; and many of the people beleeved in Jeſus <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh</hi> 2. 23 &amp; 7 31. &amp; 8 30</note>: The Phariſees ſaid, the world is gone after him <note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 12 19</note>; and after Chriſts aſcenſion there were added 3000 ſouls <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 2, 41</note>, and 5000 <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 4. 4</note>; and afterward the Diſciples were multiplyed greatly, and a great company of the Prieſts were obedient to the faith <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 6. 1, 7</note>: Now all theſe, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be called a City, a World of people, thouſands and multitudes (for the Holy Ghoſt, at the laſt, leaves num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering) could not meet together in one place for hearing the Word: For no one room in a private houſe could hold them all; no one mans voyce could reach them, much leſs could ſo many thouſands, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, at once, receive the Sacrament to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; nor could be accommodated with beds to ſit, lie, or lean upon, (which was Chriſts geſture,) a Table to receive at, and Cups to drink in; and therefore they were conſtrained to ſever themſelves into divers companies for breaking of bread <note n="p" place="margin">Act 2 46</note>, and to meet diſtributively in their private houſes for that purpoſe:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119433:20"/>
Hence it is obſervable, that though proof be offered by ſome that the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did meet together in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to heat the Word (which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Jews with Chriſtians,) and to chuſe Officers, (which is not every Lords day-work, and to which the preſence of women and children, the greater half of the Church, is not required,) yet not one word is brought to prove that they all met in one place to receive the Sacrament, the chief Church-ordinance. 2. Twelve Apoſtles <note n="q" place="margin">Math. 9. 35. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10 1</note>, ſeventy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <note n="r" place="margin">Luke 10 2</note> (beſides Elders mentioned <hi>Act.</hi> 11. <note n="s" place="margin">Act. 11. 30</note> as being extant before that time) which doubtleſs were diligent Preachers in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the chief place of their reſidence, and could not all, nor moſt of them, be imployed once every Lords day, if there was but one Congregation in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 3. The Church that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>Peter,</hi> met many of them in the houſe of <hi>Mary,</hi> and others of them, <hi>James</hi> and his brethren, elſewhere <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 12. 5. with 12 17</note>, ſo that Church did not meet in one place. 4. It is ſaid that <hi>Paul</hi> abode in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> with <hi>Peter</hi> fifteen days <note n="v" place="margin">Gal. 1. 18</note>, and doubtleſs <hi>Peter</hi> and he frequented the Church-meetings, yet he ſaw no other of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119433:21"/>
the Apoſtles, ſave <hi>James</hi> the Lords bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (he ſaith not they were not in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> but he ſaw them not) which had been very improbable if not impoſſible, (ſeeing the Apoſtles were diligent in preaching) if there had been but one Church-meeting in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> more might be ſaid to prove, that the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> conſiſted of more then one Congregation, and inſtance of the like may be given in other Churches of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria, Epheſus, Corinth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. 17. <hi>May not every Congregation enjoy all the Ordinances of God within it ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No; 1. Synods are the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God, and cannot be had in a particular Congregation; yea general Councels are the Ordinances of God, and yet cannot be found in any leſs Church then the univerſal viſible. 2. A particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, conſiſting only of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Members, cannot enjoy ordination by Presbyters, which is an ordinance of God; nor can ſhe in that ſtate regularly partake in Sacraments and Cenſures, therefore combination or conſociation of Churches is uſeful and needful in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid caſes, as alſo in caſe of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119433:21"/>
Churches inſufficiency to tranſact her own buſineſs, in caſe of buſineſs of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concernment to more Churches then one, in caſe of an incompetent particular Elderſhip, of appellation, of preſumed mal-adminiſtration, of diviſions in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, of differences between Churches, of ſpreading Hereſies indanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truth &amp; Peace, deciſion of hard queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions, direction in hard caſes, or the like <note n="w" place="margin">Act. 15</note>.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 18. <hi>Doth the Scripture war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the uſe and ſubordination of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational, Claſſical, Provincial, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and Oecumenical Aſſemblies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes, it doth. For 1. of Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Aſſemblies no queſtion is made. 2. The proving of the Church of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to conſiſt of more Congregations then one, and their Elders queſtionleſs convening for Acts of government of thoſe Congregations, doth alſo prove the warrantableneſs of a Claſſical Aſſembly. 3. There being warrant ſufficient for combination of Churches, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not limiting it to ſuch or ſuch limits, beyond which it may not exceed, doth ſufficiently warrant the greater combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as occaſion may require them, and they may with conveniency be had; the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119433:22"/>
Scripture doth not determine thoſe caſes in which a Church may call neighboring Churches together for advice, nor with how many Churches, or with what Churches ſhe ſhould adviſe, nor in what caſes neighbor Churches may call an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Church to account, or how oft they muſt do it, nor when they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully non-communion a Siſter-Church; nor doth the Scripture limit the number of Elders, as three, four, five, ſix, &amp;c. which each Congregation muſt have, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more no leſs; nor doth it bound a Congregational Church, ſaying, it muſt conſiſt of one hundred, two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, five or ſix hundred, or a thouſand, two, three, or more thouſands, nor that the bounds of the habitation of its mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhould be two, three, four, ten, twenty miles; but theſe things are left to prudence, according to the general rules of the Word. 4. How much the greater diſtance there is between Churches, ſo much the leſs needs the viſible communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof to be, becauſe danger of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal and infection, and opportunity of mutual edification is leſs or more, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the diſtance of place is greater or leſs, and this occaſions and juſtifies the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119433:22"/>
more ſtrict, ordinary, viſible, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Communion of the Congregations within a Claſſis, then within a Province, within a Nation then in all the World. 5. God requires no further aſſociation then he gives opportunity to, as in caſe a particular perſon have not opportunity of joyning to any Congregation, or a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation have no neighbors to aſſociate with, that is ſupream Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Authority to us, which is the higheſt we can get <hi>pro hic et nunc,</hi> if God by his providence ſhut the door of higher Appeals that we cannot aſcend above a National or a Provincial Aſſembly, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a particular Church; and this is true alſo in ſome neceſſary caſes, that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream civil power may be exerciſed in one Aſſembly, yea in one Family; the ſame thing may be ſaid of the Jewiſh Synagogues in Heathen Countries, that they were independent, when they could not have the benefit of ſuperior judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, though they were nothing ſo in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> where they might have that benefit. 6. In the Jewiſh Church were ſeveral diſtinct Presbyteries or Conventions of Elders, ſubordinate one to another, and as the word <hi>Preſbytery</hi> is tranſlated to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119433:23"/>
the Chriſtian Church <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 4 14.</note>, ſo that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of Presbyteries was not cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, nor typical, nor a temple-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but grounded on Reaſon, and the light of nature, as appears by <hi>Jethro</hi>'s advice to <hi>Moſes</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Exod. 18 21, 22, 23, &amp;c.</note>, and by the conſent of all Nations warrantably moulding civil Government in ſuch a ſubordination; and God hath not commanded men to lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide their reaſon, nor hath he prohibited ſuch ſubordination, but commanded it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. For. 1. Chriſt ſpeaks of a Church then extant, which could be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Jewiſh Church, (no Chriſtian Church being then founded,) with ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Judicatories &amp; appeals, and therefore muſt needs be underſtood by <hi>[tell the Church,]</hi> to command appeals from the Synagogue to the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> while the Jewiſh Church, and the Government thereof, ſtood undiſſolved. 2. There is no appearance in the words there, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, that Chriſt appointed that the Chriſtian Churches Government ſhould be moulded after another manner then the Jewiſh, in matters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of moral Equity. 3. Subordination of a particular perſon offending to a particular Church, doth by a like reaſon prove the ſubordination
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119433:23"/>
of a Church to greater Aſſemblies, becauſe the grounds, reaſons and ends of ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation are the ſame in both. 4. The El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Governors are in Scripture fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called by the name of <hi>Rahal,</hi> and by the Septuagint <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> or Church <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 31 30. with 28 Lev. 4. 14. with 15. 2 Chron. 1 2. with 3. Deut. 23. 1 2, 3, 8.</note>, and ſometimes the word <hi>Rahal,</hi> or Church is tranſlated by the 70. <hi>[the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedrion]</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26.</note>; and therefore the Apoſtles might well underſtand our Saviour, by Church, to mean the Elders, and not the whole Congregation, eſpecially he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of judicial proceedings: when the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders came alone to the Church-meeting, then but one trumpet ſounded; but if both trumpets ſounded, then both Elders and people met together in one Aſſembly <note n="c" place="margin">Num. 10 2, 4.</note>. They that interpret the word <hi>[Church]</hi> of Elders and brethren of a particular Congregation, are deſired to ſhew where Elders and Brethren, without women and children, are called a Church. 7. If there be an univerſal viſible Church, and Apoſtles, Teachers, Governments <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 28.</note> be ſeated primarily in it, and the whole is not ſubject to a part, but the part to the whole, then the neerer any Aſſembly of Churches combined comes to the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal viſible Church, the more authority it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119433:24"/>
is inveſted withall; and a general Councel is of more authority then a national, and a national then a provincial.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 19. <hi>It is granted that the Scripture doth warrant elective occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Synods, ſuch as that was,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>but doth it mention or warrant ſet, ſtated, Synodical Aſſemblies to meet monethly or yearly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is but a circumſtance of time, which followeth neceſſarily the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the things; if Synods ſit, they muſt ſit in ſome time, but what time or times they ſhould ſit doth depend upon circumſtances, and as the Church buſineſs requireth; the Scripture mentions not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtated Eccleſiaſtical meeting for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment Synodical or Congregational, that they ſhould meet weekly, monethly, &amp;c. nor any ſet Church-meetings (except the Lords day) for preaching, hearing, faſting, prayer, thankſgiving, conference; yet the Church may, upon occaſion, order weekly or monthly Congregational meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, according to the general Rules of Gods Word; the ſame may be ſaid of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Aſſemblies. 2. There is no ſuch material difference between ſtanding Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, and occaſional, neither in point of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119433:24"/>
lawfulneſs nor power, both (for ought we know) may be of like divine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Triennial ſtanding Parliaments may be as lawful and authoritative as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Parliaments. 3. There may be ſtanding Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> though differences and ſuits in Law be occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and a ſtanding Colledg of Phyſitians, though diſeaſes be occaſional. 2. As to electiveneſs; 1. It is contrary to Reaſon and Scripture, that an erroneous and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Congregation ſhall chooſe their own Judges, ſeeing it is probable they will either chooſe none at all, or ſuch as they know, before hand, are likely to be of their Judgment. 2. If thoſe that are in the right ſhould chooſe the Synod, yet ſtill the queſtion will be, who are in the right? for of diſſenting parties both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it, and neither will confeſs they are in the wrong. 3. It a thing is agreed on, that all the Churches in a Province, being offended at a Particular Congregation, may call that ſingle Congregation to account; yea all the Churches in a Nation may call one or more Congregations to account, that they may convent and call before them any perſon within their bounds, whom the Eccleſiaſtical buſineſs before
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119433:25"/>
them doth concern, may examine, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and in caſe of obſtinacy declare them to be ſubverters of the faith; may give ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Magiſtrate, in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, determine Controverſies of Faith; and their determinations are to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with great honor, and conſcientious reſpect, and obligation as from Chriſt: and if an offending Church refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their determinations, they may withdraw from them, and deny them Church-Communion, which ſentence of non-Communion may be ratified and backed with the authority of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; and therefore Synodical determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may oblige thoſe Churches which did not chooſe them, nor make any refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 20. <hi>But they cannot judg au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatively, nor excommunicate one or more offending Churches, they may only withdraw Communion from them; for if a national Synod ſhould exerciſe Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, then every member of it would be a national Officer, and have relation of Elders to all and every the Churches within a Nation; and why are they not to preach to all the Churches, as well as to rule over them, and to feed by doctrine,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119433:25"/>
as well as by diſcipline?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to the point of non-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Churches or perſons, we ſay, 1. If a Synod of Churches can proceed no further, but to non-Communion an offending Church, then the Synod hath in this no more power over a particular Church, or a particular perſon, then one brother hath over another brother, yea over a whole Church; for (they ſay) that a brother may admoniſh, declare, and withdraw Communion. 2. Separated Churches of Independents, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c. count non-Communion no puniſhment to themſelves, but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg; or, if it be a cenſure, it is no other then they inflict on all the Churches in the world beſides. 3. It is not ſuitable to the wiſdom of Jeſus Chriſt to apply the ſtrongeſt remedy for the weakeſt and leaſt dangerous diſeaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the caſe of an offending brother; and the weakeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to the moſt dangerous diſeaſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the caſe of an offending Church.</p>
            <p>2. Excommunication of Churches by Synods is a thing not known in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, but only of ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons in thoſe Churches which are moſt eminently guilty; the meeting
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119433:26"/>
at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> cenſured the falſe Teachers at <hi>Antioch</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 15.</note>, not the Church of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och:</hi> As when a Prince or State makes a a Law againſt Rebels or Traytors to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with death; in caſe an Army of ſuch Rebels or Traytors, or a whole Province rebels, this multitude doth not excuſe any one perſon of them from being obnoxious to that Law, or the penalty of it; yet it may be a reaſon why ſuch a Prince or State ſhould not, in prudence, execute that rigor of the Law upon every perſon of them, but upon ſome principal offenders; yet is that whole Province or Army of Rebels ſubordinate to that Prince or State, and the Laws thereof.</p>
            <p>3. It followeth not, that if a Paſtor be a Member of an authoritative national Aſſembly, that then he is a national Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and ſhould preach to every Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation over which he rules. For 1. As Knights and Burgeſſes in Parliament are not each of them ſeverally and ſingly Kingdom Officers, though in that body they do many authoritative acts relating to the whole Kingdom; and Colonels in a Councel of War may order the whole Army, and yet not be each of them a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Officer; ſo it is an incongruous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119433:26"/>
and unjuſt ſpeech to ſay that every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of an authoritative national Aſſembly is a national Church Officer. 2. As a Colonel doth not ſingly and ſeverally go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the whole Army, (but joyntly with others in a Councel of War,) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be expected to lead up or train every Regiment; ſo a Paſtor, who is a Member of a national Aſſembly, doth not <hi>ſeparatim</hi> govern all the Churches in a Nation, but joyntly with others, and therefore it cannot be concluded that he ſhould <hi>ſeparatim</hi> feed them. 3. All that can be concluded is this, that he ſhould feed them by doctrine, as well as by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, and ſo he doth; he with the reſt doth put forth doctrinal power to bring light to the Churches, as is acknowledged they may and ought upon occaſion; and why then may they not feed by diſcipline, as well as by doctrine? why may they not admoniſh offenders? And if they may, and this admonition be a cenſure, why may they not proceed to other acts of cenſure?</p>
            <p>4. Elders receive their power for the whole Church of Chriſt upon earth, and though the ordinary exerciſe of their power be confined to their own particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119433:27"/>
change, yet having a call, they may preach, adminiſter the Sacraments, or rule in any Congregation, or do one of theſe, and not the other, where their call, and the neceſſity of the Church requireth the one, and not the other.</p>
            <p>Queſt 21. <hi>But can you ſhew that El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders may put forth any act of power and authority over other Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes; but 1. it is acknowledged by Mr <hi>Burroughs</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Burroughs Irenicon.</note>, and (as he ſaith) by other Congregational men alſo, not only that Synods are the Ordinances of God, but alſo that the Elders thereof are to be looked upon as the Officers of Jeſus Chriſt, when they do ſuch Synodical acts as they may do in relation to many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. 2. A Miniſter may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacrament, as a Miniſter (for as a gifted man he cannot adminiſter it,) to a Member of another Church; and if to one, then to two, three, ſix, twelve, twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. which (it may be) are the whole Congregation, and that by vertue of Communion of Churches, and therefore they are ſtill conſidered as of diſtinct Churches, for Communion muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two at the leaſt, as Congregational men aſſert; and if it be lawful to do it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119433:27"/>
once, it is not unlawful to do it twice, thrice, or as often as the ſame call and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion requires it; and if he may do it when Members of other Churches come to him, he may as well do it when he goes to them, unleſs the place, or his, or their going or coming to the place do alter the caſe, which is no whit probable; and if a Miniſter may act miniſterially to the Members of one other Church, why not of two, three, or more Churches; when they are together may not the Miniſter of any of thoſe Churches adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to all of them? If he may, why may not all the Miniſters of the ſaid Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches joyn together in that Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? If no, which Elders are to be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? And if Elders may joyn together in acting miniſterially in point of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to divers Congregations, why not in point of cenſures? Where doth the Scripture require the one and not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? how comes the one to overthrow the relation of Elders and people, and not the other. 3 <hi>Tichicus</hi> of <hi>Aſia</hi> is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſeveral Churches of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Coloſs,</hi> not only as a beloved bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a gifted brother, but as a <hi>faithful Miniſter</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 6 21. 22. Col. 4. 7,</note>, and ſent to them; why
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119433:28"/>
did <hi>Paul</hi> ſend a Miniſter, and commend him to them as a faithful Miniſter, if he might not exerciſe miniſterial acts in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or both thoſe Churches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. If an Elder, in no caſe, have authority in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church; then, if he preach there by vertue of office, baptize, ordain, adminiſter the Supper, or the like, thoſe acts are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether null and void, as if they had never bin, and perſons ſo baptized or ordained ought to be re-baptized and re-ordained; for if a Major of one Corporation do the act of his authority out of his limits in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Corporation, the act is void in Law &amp; Reaſon; but Congregational men wil not aſſert, that Baptiſm, by a Miniſter of another Congregation, is void and null.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 22. <hi>But thoſe that diſſent in theſe particulars are good and gracious men, and their way ſeems to be purer then other ways; and therefore I would not have any one to oppoſe theſe men; for if the work be of God, it will ſtand; if of men, it will come to nought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> yea the firſt broachers, and chief Propoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of ancient and modern Hereſies and Errors, were reputed godly men: The Hereticks and Sectaries of <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119433:28"/>
did ſeem very holy, humble, ſpiritual Chriſtians, full of Chriſt, denying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves far; they could ſpeak excellently, and pray with ſoul-raviſhing expreſſions and affections, and yet notwithſtanding they were ſeverely cenſured, ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed others fined, others baniſhed, by our Independent brethren there <note n="g" place="margin">M. <hi>welds</hi> Epiſtle before his book of the Riſe raign, &amp;c.</note>. 2. We cannot be aſſured that other men are truly godly and gracious; they may be Hypocrites, (as the Pariſees (the word may ſignifie Separatiſts) of the ſtricteſt Sect amongſt the Jews were,) though we may not without good ground think ſo of them: <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> which took men and ſeparated them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a diſtinct Congregation <note n="h" place="margin">Num. 16 5. 16. Pſal. 106. 17.</note>, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for power and liberty <note n="i" place="margin">Num. 16 3.</note>, and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs profit too, (for if the Prieſts work might be taken from them, why not their Tythes and wages,) ſaying, <hi>all the Congregation is holy;</hi> every one of them: you Elders, <hi>take too much upon you,</hi> and that every man might excerciſe the function of the Prieſts <note n="k" place="margin">verſe 10</note>, were eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the Church to be the <hi>people of the Lord,</hi> and they murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> for oppoſing them <note n="l" place="margin">verſe 41.</note>; yea 250. Princes of the Aſſembly, or
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119433:29"/>
of the Councel of Governors; which were religiouſly affect, yea <hi>famous in the Church, men of renown, did joyn</hi> unto them <note n="m" place="margin">verſe 2.</note>; ſo well did they eſteem of them, and doubtleſs they were no Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, Hereticks, fundamentally erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, nor groſlly vicious in any kind, and yet the Spirit of God calls them wicked men <note n="n" place="margin">verſ. 26.</note>, becauſe of their Schiſm, a work of the fleſh <note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 5. 20.</note>, ſhewing men to be carnal <note n="p" place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 1. 2.</note>, the original hath it, reſtleſs and turbulent men; the Greek hath it, hard men, and the Lord did execute his wrath on them, and on the Congregation, for their ſakes <note n="q" place="margin">Num. 16 32, 44. 45, 46, 47.</note>; and this inſtance is the more pertinent, becauſe the gain-ſaying of <hi>Corah</hi> is a ſin of the New Teſtament, as well as of the Old <note n="r" place="margin">Jud. <hi>v.</hi> 11</note>. 3. The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is not who are good men, (though, if it were, there are multitudes of good men againſt their way, for one or a few for it,) but what is good and acceptable in the ſight of the Lord: For 1. They were as good and gracious men when they were Presbyterians, (as ſome were;) yea when they were conformable to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Canons, (as leading men about <hi>London</hi> were,) as now they are; yea ſo far as men can judg, they were then more
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119433:29"/>
holy, humble, heavenly, charitably affected, more mortified to the world then now; and they are not the better, if they be not the worſe for Independency. 2. A good man may act for Satan, and not diſcern it <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 16. 23.</note>; M<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Archer,</hi> an holy man, did hold &amp; broach helliſh opinions. 3. The temptation lies in this, when <hi>Angels from Heaven,</hi> men of ſingular parts and piety, <hi>preach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrines</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 1. 8. 2 Cor. 11. 15.</note>, Satan, which could catch godly men in the ſnare of Hereſie &amp; Schiſm, (not wicked men, whom he hath faſt enough in the ſtocks by the other foot,) muſt make uſe of ſuch as are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted good: A drunken looſe Miniſter can never lead a pious people into error.</p>
            <p>4. As to the ſeeming purity of that way, we know, that the Word of God is the rule of purity; whatſoever comes ſhort, or goes beyond, it is impurity; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary purity is as bad as voluntary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility: the Phariſees ſeemed to be in a purer way, and more afraid of pollution by ſinners, and more zealous in obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sabbath, then Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Popery came up under pretence of purity, piety, chaſtity and charity; if they can prove their way by Gods Word, then it is pure, if they cannot, it is impure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119433:30"/>
5. As for oppoſing them; both Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Miniſters, and others, are bound to contend in their places for the faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Saints <note n="v" place="margin">Jud. v. 3</note>, and to oppoſe falſe teachers <note n="w" place="margin">Tit. 1. 11 Revel. 2. 2 2 Joh. v. 10 11. Gal. 1 7, 8. Deut. 13. 6, 7, 8 Rom 13, 4</note>, which are ravening and grievous wolves <note n="x" place="margin">Math 7. 15. Act. 20 29</note>, which do leaven and trouble the Church <note n="y" place="margin">Act. 15 24. Gal. 5 9, 10, 12.</note>, and (as experience of this and former ages ſhews in <hi>Germany, New England,</hi> and in this Kingdom,) diſturb the civil Peace.</p>
            <p>6. Though Hereſie and Schiſm be works of the fleſh, and not from the God of Truth and Peace, yet they may ſtand a while, as <hi>Anabaptiſm</hi> did in <hi>Germany,</hi> yea a great while, (though I hope they ſhall not), as Arrianiſm, Pelagianiſm, and Popery have done<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the true way may be ſuppreſſed.</p>
            <p>7. If Independency, or Anabaptiſm, &amp;c. be either Hereſie, or Schiſm, or contrary to ſound doctrine, we are bound by Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venat (let who will expound it) to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate them, or atleaſt each in our places to endeavor to the utmoſt the extirpation of them. The known ſenſe of the Scottiſh Nation, which framed the Covenant, and for whoſe ſatisfaction the Covenant was taken, doth include Independency under
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119433:30"/>
the name of Schiſm, or at leaſt under thoſe words, Contrary to ſound doctrine; and the Engliſh could not but know this to be their ſence of it, and yet did not (that we know of) proteſt againſt it, or explane themſelves otherwiſe at the firſt taking of the Covenant, if they have done it ſithence; and that Independency is covenanted againſt, is further clear by the Parliaments publiſhing Ordinances for a Presbyterial Government (which are ridiculous and null if any one that will may plead exemption from it) by the Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> and other places, ſo expreſſing the ſence of it; and by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents themſelves, which now gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally renounce or refuſe the Covenant; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſcious it neither is, nor can be (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be made a noſe of wax) conſiſtent with their Church-way.</p>
            <p>8. It may as well be ſaid of Prelacy and Malignancy, as of Independency, that, if they be of God, they will ſtand, and if not, they will come to nought; therefore we ought to refrain from them, and let them alone, &amp; not oppoſe them; for queſtionles many of them truly feared God</p>
            <p>Queſt. 23. <hi>What is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Prelatical, Preſbyterial, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119433:31"/>
Government?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe three Governments do ſomewhat reſemble Monarchical, Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical, and Demonacratical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; The firſt give power only or chiefly to one Miniſter in a Dioceſs: the laſt gives the power only or chiefly to the people, as the Browniſts do, for they hold, that the people have a Negative Voyce, and may diſanul the acts of the Presbytery, not only <hi>in facto,</hi> (as when the Kingdom will not withdraw from one that is juſtly and judicially out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed), but <hi>in foro,</hi> that the ſentence is null and voyd in it ſelf; but the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, according to them, hath not a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Voyce, nor can diſanul the act of the people in Election of an Officer, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The middle is the right mid way between the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, conſiſting of Miniſters and other Rulers and Governors, which are choſen by, and do repreſent the people, as the Common Councel do repreſent the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> the Commons of <hi>England;</hi> and placing the Government, not wholy in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, nor in the body of the people, but in Miniſters and Elders. How the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119433:31"/>
way differs from the Independent way, may in ſome meaſure appear by what hath been ſaid: Now it differs from the Prelatical thus; The Prelate cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and counted himſelf only a Biſhop (a <note place="margin">Act. 20 17 28. Tit. 1 5, 7.</note> name common to Elders,) he challenged Juriſdiction above his Fellow-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to belong to him as a man of an higher rank, challenged that to one that doth belong to a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, did not aſſociate Congregations, but ſubjugate them to him, and himſelf would be ſubject to no Presbytery; he made the Cathedral, or Mother-Church, ſuperior in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> power to the reſt: but the Presbyterian way is a ſocial way, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween friends, confederates, brethren, where all judg, and all are judged; all things done <hi>communi Preſbyterorum conſilio;</hi> where no Congregation or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is above another Congregation or Miniſter, though the major part of them aſſociated (as of congregational mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, though equal one to another) are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the minor part; where every El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is left to enjoy the office of an Elder, and every Congregation the freedom of a Congregation, in what belongs to them, and they able to perform. The Prelates
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119433:32"/>
power was altogether extrinſecal to thoſe Congregations that were under it; they did not conſent unto it, nor ſend commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners to aſſiſt or concur in it; but Claſſes and Synods are aggregates made up out of their mutual aſſociations into one, and do in matters of common concernment ſtrengthen and help particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, walking according to rule; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch as walk not in truth and peace, but are leavened with Error and variance. The Prelates urged Subſcription, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, had their Chancellors, Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, Surrogates, &amp;c. their Courts were remote from many of the people; they were expenſive, oppreſſive, by exaction of fees; they promoted Tyranny, Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Arbitrary Government; ſuffered idle, ignorant, profane, Popiſh, Arminian, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Miniſters, which the Presbyterian Government, where it is in full ſtrength (as in <hi>Scotland)</hi> doth not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119433:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
